<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-29T20:48:06+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pietro Favaro</title><subtitle>FNRS Research Fellow | PhD Student</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ACP Summer School 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/17/ACP_summerschool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACP Summer School 2023" /><published>2023-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/17/ACP_summerschool</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/17/ACP_summerschool.html"><![CDATA[<p>From July 10 to July 14, I attended the ACP Summer School 2023 about Machine Learning for Constraint Programming which took place in Leuven. The summer school offered a wide range of talks and hands-on sessions on the use of Machine Learning for Constraint Programming.</p>

<p>The program was oriented for researchers in constraint solving (constraint programming, knowledge representation, SAT/SMT solving and more) and those at the intersection of constraint solving and machine learning. As a power systems engineer, it was sometimes challenging to understand all the subtleties of the different talks. Fortunately, the numerous hands-on sessions were the perfect opportunity to deeply understand the topic and anchor knowledge. I discovered the world of Decision Focus Learning thanks to the talk of <a href="https://ekhalil.com">Elias Khalil</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michele-lombardi-3266455?miniProfileUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_miniProfile%3AACoAAAD7_44BbfP_20oi0KycIniH8O7xWl65Ins&amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_search_srp_all%3BRFzE%2BzNSSnydpyNBLFGxzQ%3D%3D">Michele Lombardi</a>. They will surely inspire my future work.</p>

<p>One of the highlights of the summer school was the poster session and its walking diner. It is always so enriching to discuss with other about their own research and experience. I presented my work about Pumped Hydro Energy Storage and our latest results. My poster is accessible <a href="/assets/img/ACP-SummerSchool/PietroFAVARO_posterPHES.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p>I particularly liked the dynamism of the organization team lead by <a href="https://people.cs.kuleuven.be/~tias.guns/">Tias Guns</a> which prepared plenty of activities and made us discover Leuven. It is a splendid city with historical buildings at every corner and excellent museum named M. I highly recommend you visit if you ever have the opportunity.</p>

<p>As you can see in the picture below, we all had to think very hard (but with style) during the whole week!</p>

<p><img style="display: block; margin: 0 auto; width: 80%; max-width:1000px; height:auto" src="/assets/img/ACP-SummerSchool/ACPsummerschool-grouppicture.JPG" /></p>

<p>*photo by H. Verhaeghe</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From July 10 to July 14, I attended the ACP Summer School 2023 about Machine Learning for Constraint Programming which took place in Leuven. The summer school offered a wide range of talks and hands-on sessions on the use of Machine Learning for Constraint Programming.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Engie Award</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/Engie_Award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engie Award" /><published>2023-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/Engie_Award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/Engie_Award.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/EngieAward.jpeg" alt="Picture of Philippe De Raedemaeker, Scientific Director of Laborelec, Diane Thomas, Vice-rector for the transitions at UMons and Pietro Favaro, recipient of the Engie Award 2022" title="Engie Award 2022" /></p>

<p>On May 04, 2023, I was awarded the Engie Award 2022 for my Master’s Thesis on Pumped Hydro Energy Storage (PHES). This prestigious award recognizes outstanding contributions to the energy transition. During the event, co-organized by the University of Mons, I presented my work in front of esteemed colleagues, including vice-rectors, and Engie representatives from Tractebel and Laborelec. It was truly gratifying to be part of an evening dedicated to the energy transition and the positive impact of collaboration between academia and industry. Receiving the award from Philippe De Raedemaeker, Scientific Director of Laborelec, and Diane Thomas, Vice-rector for the transitions, was a particularly moving moment for me.</p>

<p>A significant aspect of my thesis focused on demonstrating the economic value of the method we employed to optimize the day-ahead scheduling of PHES. This key point was particularly appreciated by the jury. In addition, the innovative integration of machine learning within optimization in order to inform the optimization process as precisely as possible was also highlighted.</p>

<p>I am very grateful to Engie for their support in facilitating research on the energy transition and selecting my work. I will strive to keep my research relevant and valuable for the industrial actors who play a pivotal role in the success of the energy transition.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HERA Award Sustainable IT</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/26/HERA_award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HERA Award Sustainable IT" /><published>2023-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/04/26/HERA_award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/26/HERA_award.html"><![CDATA[<p><img style="float: right; width: 30%; max-width:200px; height:auto; padding-left: 10px;" src="/assets/img/HeraAwardSustainbaleITlogo.jpg" /></p>

<p>My Master’s Thesis (accessible <a href="https://hera.futuregenerations.be/sites/www.futuregenerations.be/files/2023_mtait_05_tfe_pietrofavaro.pdf">here</a>) has been awarded the HERA<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Award Sustainable IT. The HERA Awards are annual prizes aimed at fostering and supporting innovative research towards a sustainable world. Specifically, the HERA Award Sustainable IT recognizes remarkable contributions that, through a holistic sustainable approach, bring new insights or practices to the IT sector.</p>

<p>The jury highlighted the novelty of the approach and the impactful application to Pumped Hydro Energy Storage (PHES). By leveraging AI, my innovative techniques have yielded significant economic and environmental benefits in the storage of renewable electricity through PHES. Given the complexity of PHES operations, we employed a combination of machine learning and optimization to derive optimal day-ahead schedules of the units. More precisely, neural networks were utilized to model the efficiency curves of the PHES units. These neural networks were then reformulated as a set of MILP constraints and integrated into a day-ahead scheduling optimization problem. With immediate applicability to existing sites, we can optimize their efficiency and improve their short-term planning. Furthermore, the demonstrated economics of underground PHES pave the way to repurposing former quarries or mines as PHES facilities, thereby minimizing environmental impact and CAPEX costs.</p>

<p>As a young engineer deeply concerned about the climate crisis and environmental damage, receiving this award is a great honor. It recognizes not only the technical excellence of the proposed approach but also its positive societal impact. Finally, it motivates me to strive for excellence in research that contributes to a more sustainable future.
<br />
<br /></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>HERA stands for Higher Education &amp; Research Awards. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>